Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
Sokongan Admin Tonton di kissasia.cam atau kisskh.org
=The Palace Gambit=
=The Palace Gambit=
=Episode 10=
=Episode 10=
(My Fate Is in My Own Hands)
(My Fate Is in My Own Hands)
Stop right there!
Berhenti di sana!
Noble Consort Xian.
Noble Consort Xian.
Forgive me,
Forgive me,
but I don't know what I did
but I don't know what I did
to anger Consort Chun so gravely
to anger Consort Chun so gravely
that she demands my hands chopped.
that she demands my hands chopped.
I'm innocent!
I'm innocent!
I beg Your Highness to save me.
I beg Your Highness to save me.
Your Highness,
Yang Mulia,
why would a mere convict maid
why would a mere convict maid
deserve your personal attention?
deserve your personal attention?
Consort Chun.
Permaisuri Chun.
What offense did this maid commit?
What offense did this maid commit?
I've been cultivating orchids for His Majesty.
I've been cultivating orchids for His Majesty.
The fertilizer from Hard-Labor Ward
The fertilizer from Hard-Labor Ward
caused the leaves to wither.
caused the leaves to wither.
I came
I came
to take Lu Jiuning
to take Lu Jiuning
back to Yongxiu Palace to salvage them.
back to Yongxiu Palace to salvage them.
Unless she's committed serious crimes,
Unless she's committed serious crimes,
you shouldn't disable her, Consort Chun.
you shouldn't disable her, Consort Chun.
Lest people say
Lest people say
you abuse palace staff.
you abuse palace staff.
Release her!
Release her!
Noble Consort Xian,
Noble Consort Xian,
the fertilizer
the fertilizer
is my fault.
is my fault.
I'll immediately
I'll immediately
prepare new fertilizer for you.
prepare new fertilizer for you.
Come with me.
Come with me.
Yes.
ya.
Come.
Come.
(Consort Chun,)
(Consort Chun,)
(turns out)
(turns out)
(you're this desperate to eliminate me?)
(you're this desperate to eliminate me?)
(Lady Yu was right about you.)
(Lady Yu was right about you.)
(Your involvement in Wan'er's death)
(Your involvement in Wan'er's death)
(is undeniable.)
(is undeniable.)
(Yongxiu Palace)
(Yongxiu Palace)
I've sinned.
I've sinned.
Please punish me, Your Highness.
Please punish me, Your Highness.
What did you do?
What did you do?
(Yanqiu, Chief Maid)
(Yanqiu, Chief Maid)
(Yunxiang, Chief Maid) Yanqiu came to Hard-Labor Ward
(Yunxiang, Chief Maid) Yanqiu came to Hard-Labor Ward
requesting orchid fertilizer.
requesting orchid fertilizer.
I took it upon myself
I took it upon myself
to add bean cake residue to your fertilizer,
to add bean cake residue to your fertilizer,
causing mole cricket disease.
causing mole cricket disease.
So you mean
Jadi maksud awak
you lured me to Hard-Labor Ward
you lured me to Hard-Labor Ward
and used me
and used me
to rescue you from Consort Chun?
to rescue you from Consort Chun?
I anticipated
I anticipated
Consort Chun's outburst
Consort Chun's outburst
and I knew Your Highness
and I knew Your Highness
values flowers above all.
values flowers above all.
Thus
Thus
I sabotaged your fertilizer,
I sabotaged your fertilizer,
forcing you to intervene
forcing you to intervene
to save both orchids and me.
to save both orchids and me.
I manipulated Your Highness
I manipulated Your Highness
to save myself.
to save myself.
I know my guilt.
I know my guilt.
I dare not lie.
I dare not lie.
Please punish me.
Please punish me.
What insolence!
What insolence!
I know I was wrong.
I know I was wrong.
I accept punishment.
Saya terima hukuman.
Yanqiu.
Yanqiu.
Fetch her an umbrella.
Fetch her an umbrella.
Yes.
ya.
Who do you think you are, little maid,
Who do you think you are, little maid,
to scheme against me?
to scheme against me?
But given your desperation,
But given your desperation,
I'll forgive you this once.
I'll forgive you this once.
Because of you,
Because of you,
Her Highness antagonizes Consort Chun further.
Her Highness antagonizes Consort Chun further.
Show gratitude!
Show gratitude!
My deepest thanks.
My deepest thanks.
Rise.
Bangkit.
If the jade orchid dies,
If the jade orchid dies,
I
saya
shall charge you severely.
shall charge you severely.
Rest assured,
Rest assured,
bean residue won't kill it.
bean residue won't kill it.
I can save it.
I can save it.
You'd better.
You'd better.
Should I fail,
Should I fail,
I'll pay with my life.
I'll pay with my life.
I'll begin at once.
I'll begin at once.
Take the umbrella.
Take the umbrella.
Thank you.
terima kasih.
Make haste.
Make haste.
This maid
This maid
shows boldness and wit.
shows boldness and wit.
Reminds me of my younger self.
Reminds me of my younger self.
Full of passion
Full of passion
and unflinching resolve.
and unflinching resolve.
Now
Now
after years in these palace walls,
after years in these palace walls,
(Yongxiu Palace) my edges have been worn.
(Yongxiu Palace) my edges have been worn.
Seeing her
Seeing her
is like seeing my younger self again.
is like seeing my younger self again.
But Your Highness,
But Your Highness,
she's so reckless and bold,
she's so reckless and bold,
full of cunning schemes.
full of cunning schemes.
If you keep indulging her,
If you keep indulging her,
will she bring disaster upon us?
will she bring disaster upon us?
Unyielding
Unyielding
yet fiercely loyal.
yet fiercely loyal.
Such genuine devotion
Such genuine devotion
is rare treasure in this palace.
is rare treasure in this palace.
Let her stay at Yongxiu Palace.
Let her stay at Yongxiu Palace.
Discipline her.
Discipline her.
I believe
saya percaya
she
she
won't disappoint me.
won't disappoint me.
- Yes.
- Ya.
When mole crickets gnaw roots,
When mole crickets gnaw roots,
leaves wilt first before stems rot.
leaves wilt first before stems rot.
If commoners find these pests in fields,
If commoners find these pests in fields,
just boil chinaberry bark
just boil chinaberry bark
to drench the roots.
to drench the roots.
Within three days,
Dalam masa tiga hari,
plants will fully recover.
tumbuhan akan pulih sepenuhnya.
That's reassuring.
Itu meyakinkan.
I'll present this jade orchid to His Majesty soon.
Saya akan menghadiahkan orkid jed ini kepada Baginda tidak lama lagi.
Tend it meticulously these coming days.
Awasi dengan teliti pada hari-hari mendatang.
- Yes.
- Ya.
Yunxiang,
Yunxiang,
take charge of the greenhouse.
mengambil alih rumah hijau.
Yes, Your Highness.
Ya, Yang Mulia.
I'll care for the jade orchid with utmost diligence.
Saya akan menjaga orkid jed dengan bersungguh-sungguh.
Jiuning, you're so knowledgeable!
Jiuning, awak sangat berpengetahuan!
Indeed.
Sesungguhnya.
Even Xiao Zhuozi, our flower expert,
Malah Xiao Zhuozi, pakar bunga kami,
didn't notice the rotten roots.
tidak perasan akar busuk.
This orchid's meant for His Majesty.
Orkid ini dimaksudkan untuk Baginda.
You've all been so cautious,
Anda semua sangat berhati-hati,
even with the soil,
walaupun dengan tanah,
so you wouldn't know.
jadi anda tidak akan tahu.
You troublemaker.
Awak pengacau.
The infestation
Serangan itu
happened because of her!
berlaku kerana dia!
Yet you praise her?
Namun anda memujinya?
Since when do you side with outsiders?
Sejak bila anda berpihak kepada orang luar?
Her Highness ordered me
Yang Mulia memerintahkan saya
to oversee this.
untuk mengawasi ini.
Go sweep outside.
Pergi sapu kat luar.
You aren't needed here.
Anda tidak diperlukan di sini.
Yunxiang,
Yunxiang,
we all serve Her Highness.
kita semua berkhidmat kepada Yang Amat Mulia.
Jiuning will mend her ways.
Jiuning akan memperbaiki caranya.
She schemed against Her Highness and nearly doomed us all!
Dia merancang menentang Yang Teramat Mulia dan hampir membinasakan kita semua!
Have you forgotten so soon?
Adakah anda terlupa begitu cepat?
If she tampers with the greenhouse again,
Jika dia mengganggu rumah hijau lagi,
I can't take the fall!
Saya tidak boleh menerima kejatuhan!
From this day,
Mulai hari ini,
all of you must ensure
anda semua mesti memastikan
she stays out of the greenhouse.
dia tinggal di luar rumah hijau.
Not a single step near the jade orchid.
Tiada satu langkah pun dekat orkid jed.
Any mishap would doom us all
Sebarang kecelakaan akan merugikan kita semua
and implicate Her Highness.
dan melibatkan Yang Amat Mulia.
- Yes.
- Ya.
(Yongxiu Palace)
(Istana Yongxiu)
Jiuning.
Jiuning.
Greetings, Lord Ning.
Salam, Tuan Ning.
I heard
saya dengar
you destroyed Noble Consort Xian's orchid,
kamu memusnahkan orkid Permaisuri Mulia Xian,
and
dan
almost got
hampir dapat
your hands chopped off
tangan anda dipotong
by Consort Chun.
oleh Permaisuri Chun.
You keep risking your life.
Anda terus mempertaruhkan nyawa anda.
Should I call you lucky or blessed?
Patutkah saya panggil awak bertuah atau diberkati?
You jest, Lord Ning.
Anda bergurau, Tuan Ning.
I don't wish to court danger either.
Saya juga tidak mahu menggugat bahaya.
At first I thought you were merely bold,
Pada mulanya saya fikir anda hanya berani,
but you dare anything
tetapi anda berani apa sahaja
beyond imagination.
di luar imaginasi.
Ruthless enough to use anyone.
Cukup kejam untuk menggunakan sesiapa sahaja.
Speaking of which,
Bercakap tentang itu,
about that time you used me
masa tu awak guna saya
to deliver the portrait,
untuk menyampaikan potret,
how do you plan
bagaimana anda merancang
to repay this favor?
untuk membalas jasa ini?
Stop teasing, Lord Ning.
Berhenti mengusik, Tuan Ning.
I wasn't using you.
Saya tidak menggunakan awak.
You saw my desperation,
Anda melihat keputusasaan saya,
stepped forward,
melangkah ke hadapan,
and offered help.
dan menawarkan bantuan.
Even now,
Sekarang pun,
hearing I damaged Noble Consort Xian's orchid,
mendengar saya merosakkan orkid Permaisuri Mulia Xian,
you kindly sent this new plant
anda dengan hormatnya menghantar kilang baru ini
to spare me punishment.
untuk melepaskan saya daripada hukuman.
That's so noble of you.
Sungguh mulia kamu.
My gratitude, Lord Ning.
Terima kasih saya, Tuan Ning.
This Golden Hairpin Orchid
Orkid Jepit Rambut Emas ini
was specially acquired for my enjoyment.
telah diperoleh khas untuk kesenangan saya.
A prized variety,
Pelbagai yang berharga,
leaves like swords,
daun seperti pedang,
blooms as hairpins.
mekar sebagai penyepit rambut.
Then Your Highness should admire it properly.
Maka Yang Mulia patut mengaguminya dengan betul.
Why are you carrying it to Yongxiu Palace?
Kenapa awak bawa ke Istana Yongxiu?
Your Highness,
Yang Mulia,
you rushed
awak tergesa-gesa
to Dowager Consort's palace to get this
ke istana Permaisuri Janda untuk mendapatkan ini
after you learned Ms. Lu
selepas kamu belajar Cikgu Lu
destroyed Noble Consort Xian's orchids.
memusnahkan orkid Permaisuri Mulia Xian.
Although
Walaupun
you're now serving at Yongxiu Palace,
anda kini berkhidmat di Istana Yongxiu,
you've already
anda sudah
become Consort Chun's sworn enemy.
menjadi musuh ketat Permaisuri Chun.
Consort Chun holds immense power.
Permaisuri Chun mempunyai kuasa yang sangat besar.
Her family's military achievements
Pencapaian ketenteraan keluarganya
have earned His Majesty's trust.
telah mendapat kepercayaan Baginda.
She's not someone you can topple
Dia bukan seseorang yang boleh kamu tumbangkan
with petty tricks
dengan helah kecil
or minor leverage.
atau leverage kecil.
Thank you for the reminder.
Terima kasih atas peringatan itu.
It seems you know a lot about how to stay alive in here.
Nampaknya anda tahu banyak tentang cara untuk terus hidup di sini.
But my fate is in my own hands.
Tetapi nasib saya di tangan saya sendiri.
I don't believe power can eliminate
Saya tidak percaya kuasa boleh menghapuskan
all of us normal people.
kita semua manusia biasa.
Now that you're in the eye of the storm,
Sekarang anda berada di mata ribut,
you must be cautious from now on.
anda mesti berhati-hati mulai sekarang.
Your Highness.
Yang Mulia.
Your Highness?
Yang Mulia?
Your Highness!
Yang Mulia!
Has Miss Jiuning put some spell on you?
Adakah Cik Jiuning telah memanjakan awak?
Why do you act so strangely around her?
Mengapa anda bertindak begitu pelik di sekelilingnya?
I'm not under spell.
Saya tidak dijampi.
It's just that
Itu sahaja
I truly
saya benar-benar
admire her.
mengagumi dia.
Her fearless spirit
Semangatnya yang tidak gentar
and defiance of conventions
dan menentang konvensyen
are unlike anything I've ever seen.
tidak seperti apa yang pernah saya lihat.
Before,
sebelum ini,
I underestimated her.
Saya memandang rendah dia.
Why can't I see these supposed virtues?
Mengapa saya tidak dapat melihat kebaikan yang sepatutnya ini?
(Imperial Study)
(Kajian Imperial)
Your Majesty's stroke grows more vigorous.
Strok Tuanku semakin kuat.
I've recently copied scriptures,
Saya baru-baru ini menyalin kitab suci,
thinking of presenting them to Empress Dowager
berfikir untuk mempersembahkan mereka kepada Permaisuri Janda
upon her return.
sekembalinya dia.
Speaking of Her Majesty,
Bercakap tentang Baginda,
it reminds me of Talented Lady Wan's tragedy
ia mengingatkan saya pada tragedi Talented Lady Wan
after the birthday banquet.
selepas jamuan hari jadi.
That day, Talented Lady Wan's present
Hari tu, hadiah Talented Lady Wan
should've been sleeping sachets,
sepatutnya kantung tidur,
but turned out to be spirit money instead.
tetapi ternyata wang semangat sebaliknya.
Talented Lady Wan was gentle
Lady Wan yang berbakat lembut
and meticulous in her duties.
dan teliti dalam tugasnya.
She'd never curse Her Majesty.
Dia tidak akan pernah mengutuk Baginda.
Your Majesty speaks wisely.
Tuanku bercakap dengan bijak.
The incident was
Kejadian itu ialah
truly suspicious.
sungguh mencurigakan.
Yet Consort Chun
Namun Permaisuri Chun
accused Talented Lady Wan of disrespect
menuduh Talented Lady Wan tidak menghormati
and confined her to Cold Palace.
dan mengurungnya di Istana Dingin.
Then came news of her suicide.
Kemudian datang berita bunuh diri.
It's deeply unsettling.
Ia amat meresahkan.
Consort Chun's family defends the borders
Keluarga Permaisuri Chun mempertahankan sempadan
and had just won.
dan baru sahaja menang.
To maintain their morale,
Untuk mengekalkan semangat mereka,
I couldn't pursue this matter.
Saya tidak dapat meneruskan perkara ini.
Understood.
Difahamkan.
Your Majesty's truly thoughtful.
Tuanku benar-benar bertimbang rasa.
Your Majesty,
Tuanku,
Consort Chun brings loquat syrup.
Permaisuri Chun membawa sirap loquat.
Send her in.
Hantar dia masuk.
At once.
sekali gus.
Your Majesty.
Tuanku.
Rise.
Bangkit.
I heard of Your Majesty's cough,
Saya mendengar tentang batuk Tuanku,
so I prepared loquat syrup
jadi saya sediakan sirap loquat
to soothe your throat.
untuk melegakan tekak anda.
That's very thoughtful.
Itu sangat bertimbang rasa.
Your Majesty,
Tuanku,
I made this just for you.
Saya buat ini hanya untuk awak.
It should be taken warm,
Ia perlu diambil hangat,
lest it turns cold.
jangan sampai jadi sejuk.
Your Majesty,
Tuanku,
I must tend to my orchids
Saya mesti menjaga orkid saya
and take my leave now.
dan ambil cuti saya sekarang.
Go ahead.
Teruskan.
Your Highness.
Yang Mulia.
I've heard
saya pernah dengar
you cultivated precious jade orchid
anda menanam orkid jed yang berharga
and gifted it to His Majesty.
dan dihadiahkan kepada Baginda.
Pleased by this,
gembira dengan ini,
His Majesty bestowed rare flowers
Baginda mengurniakan bunga yang jarang ditemui
including a unique
termasuk yang unik
Yaohuang peony,
peony Yaohuang,
called 'Golden Thread Crown.'
dipanggil 'Mahkota Benang Emas.'
Indeed.
Sesungguhnya.
His Majesty's so thoughtful.
Baginda begitu bertimbang rasa.
I'm truly envious.
Saya benar-benar iri hati.
The Yaohuang peony
Peony Yaohuang
is the realm's treasure.
adalah khazanah alam.
The only one specimen
Satu-satunya spesimen
was gifted to Noble Consort Xian.
telah dihadiahkan kepada Permaisuri Mulia Xian.
If I come across a finer specimen,
Jika saya terjumpa spesimen yang lebih halus,
I shall gift it to you.
Saya akan hadiahkan kepada awak.
Thank you.
terima kasih.
However, this flower is exceedingly rare.
Walau bagaimanapun, bunga ini sangat jarang berlaku.
Your Majesty, how about this?
Tuanku, bagaimana dengan ini?
Her Majesty will return from the mountain retreat in a few days.
Baginda akan pulang dari pergunungan dalam beberapa hari lagi.
Let us take this opportunity
Marilah kita mengambil peluang ini
to host a flower banquet at Yongxiu Palace.
untuk menganjurkan jamuan bunga di Istana Yongxiu.
Splendid idea.
Idea yang bagus.
The palace has lacked such festivity for too long.
Istana telah terlalu lama tidak mempunyai perayaan seperti itu.
I will
saya akan
leave it to you.
serahkan pada awak.
All shall attend to admire the blossoms then.
Semua akan hadir untuk mengagumi bunga itu.
Understood.
Difahamkan.
I will devote utmost care to this banquet.
Saya akan menumpukan perhatian sepenuhnya pada jamuan ini.
Now I'll take my leave.
Sekarang saya akan ambil cuti.
(Noble Consort Xian,)
(Permaisuri Xian,)
(a flawless banquet is merely expected.)
(jamuan yang sempurna hanya diharapkan.)
(But any mishap)
(Tetapi apa-apa kemalangan)
(shall become your doom.)
(akan menjadi azab anda.)
Place it here.
Letak kat sini.
Gently.
Dengan lembut.
Set it down here.
Letakkannya di sini.
Give it here.
Berikan di sini.
Careful!
Berhati-hati!
Polish this area thoroughly.
Gilap kawasan ini dengan teliti.
Slow and careful!
Perlahan dan berhati-hati!
I've put it here.
Saya telah meletakkannya di sini.
Hmm.
Hmm.
Your Highness.
Yang Mulia.
Peonies in tender spring air
Peonies dalam udara musim bunga yang lembut
pale before the golden bloom.
pucat sebelum mekar keemasan.
I have heard
saya pernah dengar
commoners once queued with coins
orang biasa pernah beratur dengan duit syiling
just to glimpse the Yaohuang peony.
hanya untuk melihat bunga peony Yaohuang.
Now seeing it myself,
Kini melihatnya sendiri,
it truly is the king of flowers.
ia benar-benar raja bunga.
A peerless rarity indeed!
Jarang tiada tandingan sememangnya!
Your Highness,
Yang Mulia,
this is the only one specimen,
ini adalah satu-satunya spesimen,
truly priceless.
sungguh tidak ternilai.
His Majesty gifted it to you
Baginda menghadiahkannya kepada anda
because he favors you much.
kerana dia sangat menyayangimu.
Moreover, His Majesty ordered Imperial Household Department
Lebih-lebih lagi, Baginda memerintahkan Jabatan Isi Rumah Diraja
to deliver other blossoms
untuk menghantar bunga lain
to add to the splendor.
untuk menambah kemegahan.
His Majesty entrusted me to host this event
Baginda memberi kepercayaan kepada saya untuk mengacarakan majlis ini
for the ladies to marvel at this wonder.
untuk wanita kagum dengan keajaiban ini.
We shall need your assistance.
Kami memerlukan bantuan anda.
This...
ini...
Thank you, Your Highness.
Terima kasih, Yang Amat Mulia.
I shall greet the Empress Dowager.
Saya akan menyambut Permaisuri Janda.
Yunxiang will be in charge here.
Yunxiang akan bertanggungjawab di sini.
Execute your duties meticulously.
Jalankan tugas anda dengan teliti.
Not a single error will be tolerated.
Tiada satu kesilapan pun akan diterima.
- Yes.
- Ya.
We bid Your Highness farewell.
Kami mengucapkan selamat tinggal kepada Yang Teramat Mulia.
Eunuch Liu, this way please.
Kasim Liu, tolong begini.
Very well.
sangat baik.
Low-born wretches truly can't keep favor.
Orang-orang celaka yang berketurunan rendah benar-benar tidak dapat menjaga kebaikan.
Tsk!
Tsk!
We might all be implicated in their downfall!
Kita semua mungkin terlibat dalam kejatuhan mereka!
(Xiao Fuhai?)
(Xiao Fuhai?)
I've warned you to
Saya telah memberi amaran kepada anda
stay away from the greenhouse.
jauhi rumah hijau.
What do you want?
apa yang awak nak?
If our banquet fails,
Jika jamuan kita gagal,
we'll all be doomed.
kita semua akan ditakdirkan.
Now scram!
Sekarang scram!
Indeed.
Sesungguhnya.
Your Highness.
Yang Mulia.
All done?
Semua selesai?
Yes,
ya,
I've bought a minor eunuch.
Saya telah membeli seorang sida kecil.
He'll mix alum stones
Dia akan campurkan batu tawas
into all flowerpots.
ke dalam semua pasu bunga.
When watered,
Apabila disiram,
the alum will react,
tawas akan bertindak balas,
triggering a scorching boil
mencetuskan bisul yang terik
that destroys all blooms.
yang memusnahkan semua bunga.
Excellent.
Cemerlang.
Damaging the Yaohuang peony
Merosakkan peony Yaohuang
and ruining the banquet
dan merosakkan jamuan
will bring the entire Yongxiu Palace down.
akan menjatuhkan seluruh Istana Yongxiu.
That maid Lu Jiuning
Pembantu rumah Lu Jiuning itu
won't escape either.
tidak akan melarikan diri juga.
Your Highness is right.
Yang Mulia betul.
That Lu Jiuning
Lu Jiuning itu
thinks she's untouchable
rasa dia tak tersentuh
in Yongxiu Palace
di Istana Yongxiu
with Noble Consort Xian's favor.
dengan permaisuri Mulia Xian.
But
Tetapi
today is the day she dies.
hari ini adalah hari dia mati.